<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on amoalla.dev</title><link>https://blog.amoalla.dev/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on amoalla.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.amoalla.dev/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why I started this blog</title><link>https://blog.amoalla.dev/posts/why-i-started-this-blog/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.amoalla.dev/posts/why-i-started-this-blog/</guid><description>As a first post, I chose to write about why I started this blog. This will help me come back to it and give me a reason to not give up.
I have always felt the need to write about tech, to write about my discoveries as a software engineer. I want to share my findings and maybe discuss them with my fellow software development addicts. I love technology, it&amp;rsquo;s what I do for a living, it&amp;rsquo;s what I do on my free time.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a first post, I chose to write about why I started this blog. This will help me come back to it and give me a reason to not give up.</p>
<p>I have always felt the need to write about tech, to write about my discoveries as a software engineer.
I want to share my findings and maybe discuss them with my fellow software development addicts.
I love technology, it&rsquo;s what I do for a living, it&rsquo;s what I do on my free time.</p>
<p>What pulls me towards tech is that it makes my brain actively thinking.
At the end of the day, I feel like I didn&rsquo;t waste my time and I learned something new.</p>
<h3 id="writing-about-stuff-i-like">Writing about stuff I like</h3>
<p>Like I said, I really like doing tech stuff and I want to be a better developer.
I want to use this blog as a force pushing me to share what I know, and dive deeper into subjects I like so that I can fully understand and explain the inner workings of things.</p>
<p>I have many side projects under my belt, 99% of them goes unfinished.
I will use this platform as a tool to talk about the stuff I do so it can at least help other developers, and it will serve me as a personal journal.</p>
<h3 id="becoming-a-better-writer">Becoming a better writer</h3>
<p>As software engineers, we spend most of our time thinking about a solution or doing project management stuff like creating issues on Jira, sending emails to coordinate with other teams, taking notes in our technical meeting or writing documentation.</p>
<p>We actually write a lot ! But a blog post is not an outline of a meeting or a description under a screenshot.
It needs good structure, key points and some narrative to link all the components together.</p>
<p>All of this plays in making me <em>hopefully</em> a better writer.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I hope this will work well and that I will make of this a habit.
The optimal result would be that the contents of this blog will provide knowledge and benefits to the readers.</p>
<p>If it&rsquo;s not the case this can only benefit me. So it&rsquo;s a win-win situation.  ¯\_(ツ)_/¯</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>